Enums and structs
枚举和结构体
are how we define the data that makes
是我们定义构成自定义类型数据的方式。
Methods are how we define behavior
方法是我们定义自定义类型行为的方式。
Methods are similar to functions, which
方法与函数类似，
we covered in module 5.
我们在第 5 讲已经介绍过函数。
Methods are defined either in the context
方法在枚举或结构体的上下文中定义，
of an enum that we talked about in module
枚举在第 7 讲中讨论过，
or a struct from module 8.
结构体在第 8 讲中讨论过。
Review these modules to get ready for this one.
复习这些章节为本讲做好准备。
In this module, we'll take a look at when
在本讲中，我们讲探讨何时
methods are useful.
方法很有用。
We'll cover how to define methods
我们将介绍如何定义方法
and then show how to call methods.
然后演示如何调用方法。
We'll take a brief aside to mention associated
我们会简要提及关联函数
functions and how they're different from regular
以及它们与普通函数
functions and methods.
和方法的区别。
We'll wrap up by talking about the difference
最后我们将讨论
between methods that only need to read
仅需读取数据的方法
versus methods that need to be able to modify
与需要修改数据的方法之间的差异。
Let's start with when methods are useful.
让我们从方法的适用场景开始。
Let's take a look at the HockeyPlayer struct
来看一下第 8 讲中
we defined in module 8.
我们定义的 HockeyPlayer 结构体。
With just this definition,
仅凭这个定义，
we can create an instance, read from
我们可以创建实例，
its fields, change the values
读取其字段，
in the fields if the instance is mutable,
如果实例是可变的还可以修改其字段值，
but that's about it.
但基本上也就这些功能了。
We'd like to model what happens when a player
我们想要模拟球员
shoots the puck at the goal.
朝球门击球时的情况。
So, let's start by defining a function named
那么，让我们从定义一个名为
shoot_puck
shoot_puck 的函数开始，
and we'll work towards making the function into
然后逐步将这个函数转化为
a method. The shoot_puck
一个方法。shoot_puck 的函数
function will take a HockeyPlayer instance,
接收一个 HockeyPlayer 实例，
which is the player that will be shooting the puck.
也就是即将要击球的球员。
Eventually, this function could take in a lot of
最终，这个函数可能会接收大量
data about the current state of the game.
关于当前比赛状态的数据。
For now, we'll start our modeling by taking
现在，我们将从考虑
into account the number of seconds left
本节比赛剩余秒数
in the current period.
开始建模。
The actual implementation of this function
这个函数的具体实现
isn't important for the moment.
在目前并不重要。
Feel free to add an implementation of your choosing
你可以自由选择一个实现，
that looks at the player's stats
像是查看球员统计数据
and the seconds left,
和剩余秒数，
and prints out whether the puck went in the goal
并根据你希望的冰球模拟器
or not, according to how you want your hockey
如何运作来打印出
simulator to work.
冰球是否进球。
We've decided that, in our very
我们决定在我们这个
unrealistic simulation,
非常不切实际的模拟中，
all players always make their goals
所有球员总是能进球，
unless there's under 5 minutes left,
然而当最后 5 分钟时，
in which case, only players at the center
只有中锋
position have the composure to make shots,
才能保持镇定完成射门，
and players in other positions miss.
而其他位置的球员则会射偏。
This code works fine
这段代码运行正常
and prints Goal!.
并打印出“Goal!"。
However, we're not communicating
然而，我们并没有
the capabilities of our program
用最佳方式
the best way we could. In
来写这个程序。在
our hockey simulation program,
我们这个冰球模拟程序中，
the shoot_puck function only makes
shoot_puck 函数只有在
sense in the context of a HockeyPlayer
HockerPlayer 实例上下文中才有意义
instance.
。
Other types, like coach, fan,
其他类型，比如教练、球迷
or mascot can't legally
或者是吉祥物，按规定
shoot the puck.
不能击打冰球。
We're defining behavior of the hockey player
我们正在定义冰球运动员的行为，
that every hockey player should have,
这是每个冰球运动员都应具备的，
and the code would be more organized
而且如果行为能明确与
if the behavior was clearly tied to the
结构体关联，代码会更加有条理
struct.
。
That's where methods come in.
这就是方法的用武之地。
How do we define a method?
我们如何定义方法呢？
Let's find out.
让我们来了解一下。
Methods are defined within a block
方法定义在
that starts with the impl keyword,
以 impl 关键字开头的代码块里，
which is short for implementation.
impl 是 implementation 的缩写。
Then we specify what we're implementing
然后我们指定为谁实现
methods on, which, in this case,
方法，在这个例子中，
is the HockeyPlayer struct.
就是 HockeyPlayer 结构体。
Note that this code would look similar if
注意如果我们是为枚举类型实现方法
we were implementing a method on an enum
这段代码看起来会和此处为结构体实现方法
rather than a struct.
类似。
We'd just put the name of the enum where
我们只需要把枚举类型名放在
we currently have the name of the struct.
现在结构体名称的位置即可。
Next comes curly brackets to start the body
接下来用大括号开始
of the block. Within
代码块的主体。在
the block, we use the fn keyword
代码块内，我们使用 fn 关键字
and the method name,
和方法名，
just like with functions.
就像函数一样。
A big difference between functions
函数和方法的一个重大区别
and methods is that the first parameter
是第一个参数，
of a method is always a form
方法的第一个参数始终是
of self, which refers
某种形式的 sefl,指向
to the type that we're defining the method on –
方法实现的这个类型，
in this case, a HockeyPlayer instance.
在这个例子中就是 HockeryPlayer 实例。
The rest of the parameters of the method
方法的其余参数
are the same as the rest of the parameters of the function
和我们之前定义的函数相同
we had.
。
And whatever implementation you have would be the
里面的无论如何具体实现都
same as well, except wherever
保持不变，除了
you used the HockeyPlayer parameter,
使用 HockeyPlayer 参数的地方，
you'd use self
你现在要用 self
instead.
来替代。
Now that we have a method defined, what
现在我们定义了一个方法，那么
does it look like to call it?
调用它又是什么样子呢？
Instead of having the function name
与使用函数名
and passing the HockeyPlayer instance
并传递冰球运动员实例
as the first argument,
作为第一个参数不同，
we can specify the HockeyPlayer instance,
我们可以指定冰球运动员实例，
then a dot, then the name
然后加一个点，再输入
of the method we want to call,
我们想要调用的方法名，
and the remaining arguments that aren't self.
以及除 self 外的其余参数。
Now this code works just like the code
现在这段代码的运行效果
where shoot_puck was a function,
与 shoot_puck 作为函数时完全一样，
but we've more clearly communicated that
但我们更清晰地表达了
shooting a puck is behavior that a hockey
击球是冰球运动员实例
player instance has.
所具备的行为。
Related to methods are associated
与方法相关的是
functions. Let's take
关联函数。让我们
a look at associated functions for a minute
来简单看一下关联函数，
and see how they compare
看看它们与
with regular functions
常规函数以及
and with methods.
方法的区别。
Associated functions are defined
关联函数定义在
within an impl block on a struct
结构体或枚举的实现块中，
or an enum, the same as methods.
这与方法相同。
They're still behavior that's related to the type,
它们仍然是与该类型相关的行为，
so we want to organize that behavior
因此我们希望将这些行为组织起来，
so that it's associated
使其与类型
with the type. Unlike
相关联。与
methods, they don't take self
方法不同，它们不将 self
as a parameter. Associated
作为参数。关联函数
functions are commonly used to create
通常用于创建
instances of types, so
类型实例，
they don't have a self instance to operate
因此它们没有可操作的 self 实例
on.
。
For example, here's an associated
例如，这里有一个
function named new
名为 new 的关联函数，
that creates an instance of a HockeyPlayer
它根据给定的
struct from the given name,
姓名、
number, and position.
号码和位置创建 HockeyPlayer 结构体实例。
This function always starts the goals_ytd
该函数总是将 goals_ytd 字段
field at 0.
初始化为 0.
Note that new isn't a special
请注意，new 在 Rust 中并非
function name in Rust like it is
像 Ruby 等语言那样
in languages like Ruby,
是特殊函数名，
but by convention, many Rust types
但按照惯例，许多 Rust 类型
define an associated function named
会定义一个名为
new
new 的关联函数
that creates new instances of that type.
用于创建该类型的新实例。
To call an associated function,
要调用关联函数，
specify the type name, then two
请指定类型名称，然后
colons, then the function name.
两个冒号，再跟函数名。
The associated function is namespaced
关联函数被置于类型名之下，
beneath the type name.
形成自己的命名空间。
This code will function similarly to the code
这段代码的功能与之前
we had before in that we have
我们拥有的代码类似，
a new HockeyPlayer instance.
都是创建一个新的冰球运动员实例。
The difference is the goals_ytd
区别在于年度进球数字段
will be 0 instead of 7.
将会是 0 而不是 7.
Returning to methods,
回到讨论方法上，
let's talk about the different forms of self
我们来聊聊方法中
that a method can take, which
self 的不同形式，
has to do with whether the method only needs to
这关系到方法是否只需要
read data
读取数据
or whether it needs to write data too.
还是也需要写入数据。
We actually glossed over a problem our code
我们实际上忽略了当前代码存在的
currently has: a player
一个问题：一个球员实例
instance can only shoot the puck once.
只能击球一次。
If we try to have the same player shoot the puck
如果我们尝试再次让同一个球员再次击球
again,
，
we get an error saying use
就会收到错误提示：
of moved value: 'player'.
使用了已移动的值：'player'。
This has to do with Rust's system
这与 Rust 的所有权系统
of ownership
有关，
and the next unit is all about ownership,
下一章节将全面讲解所有权概念，
so don't worry about understanding why this error
所以不必急于此时理解
happens right this second.
为何会出现这个错误。
A better way to define the shoot_puck
在这个场景下定义
method in this context
shoot_puck 方法
is for it to borrow self instead
更好的方式是使用借用
of taking ownership, which we
而不是获取所有权，
indicate with an &amp;.
我们使用 & 符号来表示借用。
Again, we're
再次强调，
going to go into a lot more detail on this
我们将在下一章节深入探讨
in the next unit.
这个主题。
Making this change fixes the error
进行这个修改后错误就修复了，
and we can now call shoot_puck more
现在我们可以多次调用击球方法了
than once.
。
&amp;self is for methods
&self 用于那些
that don't change anything about self's
不会改变 self 值的方法
values. In this
。
implementation, we're only reading
在这个实现中，我们只是读取
from the position field of the HockeyPlayer
HockerPlayer 实例的 position 字段
instance, not changing anything.
而不做任何修改。
Let's say we did want to change self
假设我们确实想要修改 seflt,
to increase the count of the goals_ytd
在击球
when shooting the puck
且得分时
and the player gets a goal.
增加 goals_ytd 的计数。
If we make this change
当我们做了这个修改
and try to compile the code,
并尝试编译代码时，
we get an error that we cannot assign to the
会得到一个错误提示，说我们不能对
field, goals_ytd.
goals_ytd 字段赋值。
Just like we have to explicitly annotate
就像我们必须显式标注
variables that can be mutated,
可变变量一样，
we have to annotate methods that can mutate
我们也必须在可修改 self 的方法上标注
self.
。
We do this by making the first parameter of
我们通过将方法的第一个参数设定为
the method &amp;mut self.
&mut self 来实现这一点。
This fixes the error,
这样就修复了错误，
and we can see that the method has modified
我们可以看到方法已经
the player instance.
修改了 player 实例。
In this module,
在本讲中，
we covered how methods
我们介绍了如何用方法
let us add behavior to data types,
为数据类型添加行为，
how to define and call methods,
如何定义和调用方法，
associated functions defined in impl
以及在 impl 实现块中，
blocks that are associated
定义和类型相关联的
with a type
关联函数，
but not with an instance of the type,
而这个函数和类型实例无关，
and the various forms of self that
以及方法根据
methods take depending on whether they read
读取或写入数据的需求
or write data.
所采用的各种 self 形式。
Those are the basics of methods
这些就是方法的基础知识，
and the end of the syntax introduction for this
也是本章语法介绍的结尾
course.
。
Next unit,
下一章，
we'll find out all about the concepts of ownership
我们将全面了解所有权和
and borrowing.
借用的概念。
We'll get comfortable with when we should be adding ampersands.
我们会熟悉何时应该添加 & 符号。